[苏切塔]在1986年的金融危机中，哈尔沙德成功挽救了自己的声誉
[Sucheta] In the crash of 1986, Harshad had managed to save his reputation
但他已经意识到……
But he had begun to realise
自掏腰包，不是做大生意的好方法
that dipping into ones own pocket, was not the way to run a large-scale business
为了扩大规模，他需要大笔资金
To scale up, he needed big funds
因此，哈尔沙德开始敲响金融机构的大门
and Harshad started knocking at the door of financial institutions
然而只有一个人能完全打开这扇门
And there was only one man who could open this door completely
印度单位信托基金会主席（UTI） M · J · 弗拉瓦尼
The Chairman of the Unit Trust of India, M J Pherwani
最初的大公牛
The original Big Bull
在共同基金和私人投资出现之前
Before the advent of mutual funds and private investments
只有两个地方可以让印度纳税人安全地投资
there were only two places where Indian taxpayers could safely invest their money
LIC 和 UTI
LIC and UTI
尽管 LIC 是一家长期机构投资者
While LIC was a long-term institutional investor
尔UTI坐拥2万亿卢比的资金，用于投资股市
UTI had a corpus fund of 20,000 crores to invest in the share market
如果 UTI 决定买入，Sensex 指数肯定会迅速上涨
If UTI decided to buy, the Sensex was sure to gallop ahead
如果它决定出售，Sensex 指数就会下跌
And if it decided to sell, the Sensex would get reigned in
- 请坐-谢谢，先生-谢谢
- Please - Thank you, sir - Thank you
我一直很想见见你们俩
Ive been wanting to meet you both for a while now
- 很高兴见到你-我也是，先生
- Glad to meet you - Same here, sir
在我们谈生意之前
Before we talk business
我想问你们一个很重要的问题
I want to ask you guys a very important question
您尽管问
Please
你知道世界上最有价值的东西是什么吗？
Do you know what is the most valuable thing in the world?
呃
Uhh
不是手表
Its not a watch
也不是昂贵的威士忌
Not even expensive scotch
甚至也不是豪车、钻石
Not even those big cars, diamonds
都不是
No Nothing
- 建议?-呃
- Advice? - Uh
你知道 有时候一条建议可以改变你的生活 ？
You know sometimes a piece of advice can change your life?
我给你个提示
Let me give you a hint
这个词是我公司名称的一部分
That word is a part of my companys name
- 信任?-没错，就是信任
- Trust? - Correct Trust
你知道为什么信任如此重要吗？
Do you know why trust is so valuable?
因为它的需求量很大
Because its in great demand
而且总是供不应求
And is always in short supply
非常正确
Very true
现在的问题是，我为什么要相信你? 为什么？
Now the question is, why should I trust you? Why?
你完全可以信任我们
Well, you can very well trust us
- 事实上我们的整个生意-13个月零10天前
- In fact, our entire business is - Precisely 13 months and 10 days ago
我的一些 Vam Organics 股票落入了某人手中
a few of my Vam Organics shares landed up in someones hands
由于一个简单的笔误
Owing to a simple clerical mistake
[ Pherwani ]我的办公室试图联系他们
[Pherwani] My office tried to contact them
但是，你知道他们做了什么吗？
But, do you know what they did?
他们利用这个办事员的错误，卖掉了那些股票
They used this clerical mistake to their advantage and sold those shares
- 先生那个-你卖了那些股份
- Sir, that - You sold those shares
- 那些股份都是你的-先生实际上
- Those shares had landed up with you - Sir, actually, what happened was
一定是有什么误会
There is some big misunderstanding
你的股份从来没有到过我们这里
None of your shares ever came to us
- 就算真的到了我们这里，我们又怎么会卖掉?-别说了！
- And even if they did, how could we have sold them? - Stop! Please, stop
不用给我讲我们的系统是如何运作的
Dont try to teach me how our system functions
你知道我为什么想见你们吗？
Do you know why I wanted to meet you guys?
因为我想告诉你
Because I wanted to tell you
系统里可能有漏洞
there could be a loophole in the system
但只有少数人会滥用它
But only a few people misuse it
像你们这样的人
People like you
我做生意不只是为了交易
I dont do business just for the sake of a deal
我只和我信得过的人做生意
I do business with people whom I can trust
没有信任
No trust
不谈生意
no business
你知道这为什么被称为神的饮料吗？
Somras Do you know why this is called the drink of the Gods?
因为星期天喝它，会让星期一感觉像天堂
Because drinking it on Sunday, makes Monday feel like heaven
喝一小口，你不会上瘾的，来吧
Have a sip You wont get addicted with a sip Come on
不了，谢谢
No, thank you Im okay with my Thums Up
好吧
Okay?
我的猎豹
My Cheetah
在过去的六个月里你收购了 LIC GIC 和 Can Mutual
in the past six months, youve bagged LIC, GIC, Can Mutual
每笔交易都能拿到15% 的佣金
and pocketed 15 per cent commission in every deal
我的机构经纪人
My institutional broker, huh?
- 什么，普拉那夫?-你说你没事？
- What, Pranav Bhai? - And you say youre okay?
几乎算不上机构经纪人
Hardly an institutional broker
UTI 还没有给我们任何业务
UTI still hasnt given us any business
我已经厌倦了这种15% 的游戏
And Im tired of this 15 per cent game
机构有这么多钱，却没有计划
Institutions have so much money but no plan
老实说，如果我有那么多钱
To be honest, if I had that kind of money
指数会上涨4000点
the market would have been up by 4,000 points
那就拿去吧，这是你的钱，拿去投资吧
Then take it up Its your money, go on and invest it
你说什么来着? 风险是生活的调味品 ，对吗？
Whats that you say? Risk is the spice of life, right?
亲爱的，威士忌也很危险
Darling, whiskey is risky too
要不你也尝尝这个，来吧
Have a taste of this spice too Come on
你真是不可理喻
You are impossible
嘿，普拉纳夫 · 谢斯，你的笑声在一英里以外都能听到
Hey, Pranav Sheth, your laughter can be heard from a mile away
阿贾伊大哥！
Ajay Bhai!
太好了，我很高兴你离我只有一英里远
Wonderful Im glad you were just a mile away
因为我的笑声传不到加尔各答
coz my laughter cant reach all the way to Calcutta
- 干杯-干杯
- Cheers! - Cheers
- 普拉那夫! -什么事？
-[Man] Pranav! - Yes?
你不能喝酒，但是你可以拿着它，对吧? 给你
You cant drink, but you can hold it, right? Here
去吧，表达你的敬意，大个子
Go on, pay your respects Big man
呆在这儿别动
Stay right here
嘿，你好吗?
[Pranav] Hey, howre you?
阿贾伊大哥，我是哈尔沙德
Ajay Bhai, Harshad
-哈尔沙德 · 梅塔 -阿贾伊 · 凯迪亚，干杯
- Harshad Mehta - Ajay Kedia Cheers
哦不，这是普拉那夫的酒
Oh no no This is Pranav Bhais
我不喝酒，顺便说一下，我听说过很多关于你的事
I dont drink By the way, Ive heard a lot about you
自从我进入这个市场，我就听说了加尔各答的凯迪亚先生
Ever since Ive entered the market, Ive heard of Mr Kedia from Calcutta
1982年的黑色星期四，股市崩盘 ？
That Black Thursday crash of 1982?
你和信实股份的 ？
yours and Reliances?
那天我也损失了十万卢比
I too lost lakhs that day
我的意思是，我那时正要从市场上卷铺盖走人
I mean, I was on the verge of packing up from the market Bag and baggage
哈里什，对吧？
Harish, right?
- 哈尔沙德，哈尔沙德・梅塔-哦对，哈尔沙德
- Harshad Harshad Mehta - Yes, Harshad
给你一句忠告，哈沙德
A word of advice for you Harshad
如果你承受不了这么大的压力，就趁早走人，好吗？
If you cant take the heat, get out of the kitchen Huh?
不是那样的
Its not like that
如果我们结束了你的股市生涯，我真的很抱歉
And Im really sorry if we ended your stint in the market
- 嗯? 非常抱歉-不不
- Hmmm? Very sorry about that - No, no
事实上，我现在已经开始做咨询工作了
In fact, Ive started my own consultancy now
- 你的?-是的
- Yours? - Yes
高摩投资
Growmore
好吧，高摩先生
Alright, Mr Growmore
回头见
I will see you around
如果你能留在市场上
if you stay around
过来
Come here
梅塔先生，我的饮料呢？
Oh, Mr Mehta? Wheres my drink?
我的天！
Bloody hell!
你把我的酒喝完了？
You finished my drink?
这个凯迪亚到底是谁？
Who the hell is this Kedia?
他的态度是怎么回事？
Whats with his attitude?
他当然有自己的态度
Of course he has an attitude
他实际上拥有股票市场，他来自一个商人家庭
He practically owns the share market He comes from a family of traders
他同时管理着四家公司
He manages four companies simultaneously
一只脚在货币市场，另一只脚在股票市场
One foot in the money market and the other in the share market
政府债券、 PSU 债券  规模巨大
[Pranav] Government securities, PSU bonds At a huge scale
货币市场？
Money market?
政府债券有这么多钱可以赚吗？
Is there so much money to be made in government securities?
那是财富的集市，兄弟！
Its the bazaar of wealth, brother!
告诉我一件事，我们的股票市场每天的成交量是多少？
Okay, tell me one thing What is the daily volume of our share market?
大约一千亿卢比
Around 10,000 crores
猜猜货币市场每天的成交量是多少? 两万亿卢比
And guess the daily volume of the money market? Two lakh crores
因此，态度
Therefore, attitude
阿什温，你见过板球运动员打网球吗？
Ashwin, have you ever seen a cricketer play tennis?
即使在网球场上，也有草地球场、红土球场  而且每个球场的比赛都不同
But even in tennis, there is a grass court, a clay court and the game is different for each
这种货币市场游戏超出了你的能力
This money market game is out of your league
哈沙德，这六个月来一切都很顺利
[Ashwin] Harshad, its all been going well for six months
- 为什么这么着迷?-什么进展顺利？
- Now why this new obsession? - Whats been going well?
高摩只是我们的公司名字，增长在哪里？
Growmore is just our name, wheres the growth?
机构经纪业务还不够好
Institutional broking is not good enough
我们必须想出一些新的东西
We have to think of something new
业务达到饱和点，而不是大脑，或者说我们也应该让大脑饱和了？
Businesses reach saturation points, not brains Or do we stop using our brains as well?
我明白了
I get it
那个阿贾伊 · 凯迪亚，他吓到你了，对吧？
That Ajay Kedia, hes rattled you, right?
所以，你现在是在给我们上课
[Pranav] And so, youre lecturing us now
你为什么不说清楚点
Why dont you speak clearly
因为他对你态度不好，你就要搞他吗？
that you want to stick a finger up his, for the way he treated you?
这里有人知道货币市场是什么吗
[Ashwin] Does anyone here even know what the money market is?
你有什么可靠的计划吗？
Do you have any solid plan in mind?
这才是正确的问题
Now thats the right question
看，股票市场和货币市场并没有很大的不同
Look, the share market and money market arent very different
在这里，我们交易的不是股票，而是
Here, instead of shares, we trade in
政府证券，PSU 债券和单位
government securities, PSU bonds and units
我们都知道经纪人了解公司股票的价值
We all know that a broker understands a companys shares value
比公司更了解，对吧？
better than the company itself, right?
是的
Yes
同样，在货币市场
Similarly, in the money market
哪些银行想要购买有价证券，以及他们从哪里可以得到这些证券
which banks want to buy securities and where they can get them
消息来源都是经纪人
is in the brokers knowledge
我们的工作是同时管理需求和供应
[Harshad] Our job is to manage both demand and supply
每笔货币市场交易中最重要的文件就是SGL
The most important document in every money market transaction is the SGL note
SGL 是指明细总帐
SGL means Subsidiary General Ledger
[阿什温]现在让我们假设，我从你那里买了1000手
[Ashwin] Now lets assume, I buy 1000 units from you
所以，你给我一张 SGL 的票据作为回报
So, you give me an SGL note in return
我把这个 SGL 存在 PDO 里
I deposit this SGL in the PDO
PDO是印度储备银行的公共债务办公室
that is Public Debt Office of the RBI
PDO 拥有你所有债券的交易记录
The PDO holds the account for all your units
经纪人、银行  每个人都希望自己的业务快速增长
[Harshad] Brokers, banks everyone wants their business to grow fast
他们说，SGLs 减慢了交易速度
And they say, SGLs slow down transactions
因此，我们将使用 BR 代替 SGL
So, instead of SGL, we will use BR
- ‘ BR 意思是银行收据-‘ Hmm
-[Bhushan] BR meaning Bank Receipt -[Rebello] Hmm
这意味着，即使没有SGL，交易也是可以进行的
That means transactions are now possible without SGL
不需要中央权威
There is no central authority
现在，当一家银行想把自己的证券卖给另一家银行时
Now, when one bank wants to sell its securities to another
他们可以简单地开一张收据
they can simply issue a receipt
保证他们有证券
guaranteeing that they have the securities
我们在花旗银行有联系人吗
[Ashwin] Do we have a contact in Citibank?
我们没有，但我已经安排了和 K · S · 特亚吉的会面
[Harshad] We dont have a contact but Ive fixed a meeting with K S Tyagi
他处理所有的货币市场交易
he handles all their money market deals
他在市场上被称为八木（印度板球运动员）
Hes known as Tyagu in the market
梅塔先生，你有没有能力并不重要
Mr Mehta, its not important whether youre capable or not
重要的是你是否了解这个市场
What is important is whether you understand this market
首先，了解这个市场，然后我们再谈
First, learn about this market and then approach us
那我们走着瞧吧
Then well see
你是说，因为我们是局外人，你就不和我们做生意？
You mean to say, you wont do business with us because we are outsiders?
这不是局内人或局外人的问题
Its not a question of insider or outsider
我已经有了我现有的经纪人
I already have my existing set of brokers
为什么我要和新人一起工作？
Why should I work with somebody new?
先生，曾经有一段时间，我在股票市场也是新手
Sir, there was a time, I was new at the stock markets too
但我走出了自己的路
But I found my way through it
因此，我相信我也可以在货币市场上做到这一点
So, I am sure I can do it with money markets too
梅塔先生，让我给你一些建议
Mr Mehta, let me give you some very good advice
这是货币市场
This is the money market
来自股票市场的顶级经纪人想要进入这个市场，是不可能的
Top brokers from the stock market want to enter it, but they cant
你知道为什么吗? 因为血统
You know why? Because of pedigree
血统在这里非常重要
Pedigree is very important here
[ Tyagi ]这个市场没有新人的位置
[Tyagi] Theres no place for new people in this market
你也不应该尝试
You shouldnt try either
谢谢你的建议，先生
Thank you for your advice, sir
但我不确定这个建议对你还是对我有利
But I am not sure if it was in my interest or yours
祝你今天过得愉快
Have a good day
嗨
Hi
那是谁？
Whos that?
阿贾伊 · 凯迪亚
Ajay Kedia
好吧
Okay
嗨
Hi
- 等一下-抱歉打扰了
- Just a second - I am sorry to interrupt you
没关系
Thats okay
我能见见你们的财政部长内拉吉·乔普拉先生吗？
Can I see your treasury chief, Mr Niraj Chopra?
你今天和他有预约吗？
Did you have an appointment with him today?
告诉他是哈尔沙德·梅塔
Just tell him its Harshad Mehta
嗯  对不起，先生，他现在不在
Uhm Sorry, sir, but he is not available
你能给我预约一个明天见他的时间吗？
Can you give me an appointment with him for tomorrow?
先生，恐怕他明天就要去马德拉斯了
Sir, Im afraid but hes leaving for Madras tomorrow
他要离开一段时间
He will be out of station for a while
那么，他白天一点时间都没有？
So, he has no time during the day at all?
他要赶飞机
He has a flight to catch
内拉吉兄弟
Niraj Bhai
太巧了! 哇！
What a coincidence! Wow!
我是哈沙德，哈沙德 · 梅塔
Im Harshad, Harshad Mehta
- 你好-你好
- Hello - Hello
在印度
In India
货币市场不是西方意义上的市场
the money market is not a market in the Western sense of the term
在这里，它更像是一个丛林
Here, its more like a jungle
我并不惊讶八木把你赶出来
[Niraj] Im not surprised Tyagu threw you out B*****d
他不给我们任何业务，也不让我们自己做
He doesnt give us any business nor does he let us do it on our own
他为什么要招待你？
Why would he entertain you?
- 听着，哈沙德，对吗?-是的
-[Niraj] Look, Harshad, right? - Yeah
花旗银行是这片丛林的王者
Citibank is the king of this jungle
他们把整个货币市场变成了一个高级俱乐部
Theyve made the whole money market into an exclusive club
他们不喜欢外人
And they do not like outsiders
今天，货币市场就像是一家银行及其经纪人的领地
Today, the money market feels like the territory of one bank and its brokers
这是个该死的垄断集团
Its a goddamn cartel
而八木就是集团的老大
And Tyagi, hes the boss of this cartel
他的经纪人，阿贾伊·凯迪亚，Hiten Shroff，哈曼德拉·卡帕迪亚
And his brokers, Ajay Kedia, Hiten Shroff, Hemendra Kapadia
这些人垄断了大部分的货币市场
these people have cornered most of the money market
我们只能听天由命了
We are at their goddamn mercy
我们一达成协议，他们就会知道
The moment we crack a deal they get to know
简单来说
In simple words
这种饼干就是市场
This cookie is the market
集团正享受着整块饼干的美味
And the cartel is enjoying eating the whole cookie
我明白了
No, I get it
花旗银行与八木和他的经纪人有自己的集团
Citibank has its own cartel with Tyagi and his brokers
那么，为什么我们不能建立自己的集团来对抗他们呢？
So, why cant we form our own cartel against them?
不，我是认真的
No, Im serious
老实告诉我，你从来没有想过这个吗？
Tell me honestly, Niraj Bhai Have you never thought of this?
当然想过，事实上经常想
Of course, I have Often, in fact
就像这样，我也有很多其他的幻想
And like this, I have many other fantasies too
但我们有武德
But we also have ethics
八木和他的团伙不讲武德
Tyagi and his cartel know no ethics
我们不能像他们那样做肮脏的交易
We cant do dirty business like them
我明白，你不应该做肮脏的生意
I understand You should never do dirty business
但我可以，对吧？
But I can, right?
你觉得
Do you think
八木真的知道他的经纪人是怎么给他拉生意的？
Tyagi really knows how his brokers bring him business?
是也不是
Yes and no
所以同样的，你不需要知道我是如何帮你得到这笔生意的
So similarly, you dont need to know how I get you the business
你指路，告诉我从哪里开始
You show the path Just tell me where to start
我的时间，我的努力
My time, my effort
你没有任何损失
And you have nothing to lose
你知道我会坐这班飞机，对吧？
You knew I was going to be on this flight, right?
是也不是
Yes and no
集团的成功离不开优秀的人才
A cartel is as good as its members
我们今天要见的人
The man were meeting today
是你们集团的潜在成员
Hes a potential member to your cartel
我们的集团
Our cartel
你的集团
Your cartel
我在 Grindlays 有很多熟人
I have many contacts at Grindlays
我以前在 Grindlays 工作
I used to work at Grindlays
已经证实
Its confirmed that
Grindlays 在寻找货币市场经纪人
Grindlays is on the look-out for money market brokers
他们不想要花旗银行集团的任何人
And they dont want anyone from the Citibank cartel
这一切都没问题，但最大的问题是花旗银行(Citibank)
All that is fine, but the biggest problem is, Citibank
他们有足够的资金购买这些证券
They have all the funds to buy the securities
一旦他们垄断市场，他们的经纪人就可以操纵一切
Once they corner the market, their brokers manipulate everything
看来你不看电视
Seems like you dont watch TV
当然
Of course
那么，你没看到
Well then, havent you seen
一只麻雀，然后是一群麻雀  在地上啄食种子
one sparrow, then more sparrows Land to peck at some seeds
解决办法就在于此
The solution lies within that
什么？
What?
听着，花旗银行扔的是鸟食
Look, Citibank throws birdseed
每家银行都开始啄它，太孤立了
And like a sparrow, every bank begins pecking on it, that too alone
因此，很容易陷入困境
And so, its easy to get trapped
你想说什么？
And whats your point?
我是想说，现在是所有银行团结起来的时候了
The point is, its time for all banks to come together
像这样，我们是一体的
Like this We are one
我们很坚强，我们很勇敢
We are strong We are courageous
一旦我们团结起来，我们就能做大事
Once we unite, we can achieve big things
我们不能和任何银行打交道
We just cant deal with any bank
我们还必须考虑利润和损失
We also have to think about profit and loss
就这一次，拍打你的翅膀，和猎人的网一起飞走
For once, flap your wings together and fly off with the hunters net
利润会随之而来
Profit will follow
一旦花旗银行及其经纪人失去交易
And once Citibank and its brokers lose a deal
我们可以剪断他们编织的网
we can cut the net they have woven
听着，我是股票市场的人
Look, Im a man of the share market
我认为是长期的
I think long-term
如果作为一个经纪人，我准备承担损失，你们毕竟是银行
If as a broker, I am ready to bear a loss You are banks after all
你觉得怎么样？
What do you say, Niraj Bhai?
一，二，三
One, two, three
我们开始吧
Lets do it
聪明的小麻雀 聪明的小麻雀
Clever little sparrows Smart little sparrows
他们走了  带着网走了
Off they go carrying the net along
聚集在一起，羽毛相同的鸟儿
flocking together, birds of a feather
我听说 Grindlays 也和哈尔沙德联手了？
I hear that Grindlays too has joined hands with Harshad?
他们不再与我们合作了
Well They are not dealing with us anymore
此外，哈沙德正在接触许多小银行
Plus, Harshad is going after many small banks
还有那些我们甚至都没碰过的机构
and institutions that we dont even touch
但是他正在获得大量的信息
But he is getting volumes
他正在尽可能多地购买
Hes buying as much as he can
甚至还亏本买了一些
He has even bought some at a loss
他是白痴吗？
Is he an idiot?
老实说，哈沙德
[Niraj] Honestly Harshad
我不认为花旗银行集团现在真的会视我们为威胁
I dont think the cartel will really bother about us right now
是的，我们可能有些生意，但是离他们很远
Yeah, we may have some business but nowhere close to them
而且可能永远不会，因为花旗银行控制着这个盘子
And we never will because Citibank controls the volume
- 就这么简单-是时候了
- Its simple as that - Its time
去找安全交易的大老板 比花旗银行还要大的银行
to go to the big boss of security dealings The bank which trumps Citibank
花旗银行可能是货币市场的老大
Citibank may be the don of the money market
但谁是印度银行业的皇帝呢？
but whos the emperor of banking in India?
要打击花旗银行，我们必须考虑本地化
To fight Citibank, we must think local
你看，先生，我们已经对货币市场做了详细的研究
[Harshad] You see, sir We have done our detailed study in the money market
有很多外国银行，有交易商，有集团
There are a lot of foreign banks, there are dealers, there are cartels
他们赚了不少钱
and they are making good money
我真的认为 SBI（印度国家银行） 在这个问题上需要更积极一点
I would really say that SBI needs to be a little more aggressive in this
所有这些数据
And all this data
我们在高摩做了可靠的研究，这是绝对可行的
is absolutely backed by the solid research that we have done at Growmore
我们知道，印度国家银行经常对债券有巨大的需求
We know that SBI often has huge demand for bonds
由于来自机构投资的
Because of the heavy investments
大量投资，对吗？
coming from institutional investors, right?
我们可以轻易为你找到这些证券
And we can easily source these securities for you
事实上，没有必要担心
In fact, theres no need to be worried
所有的交易都是安全的
All transactions will be safe
我们将为您提供市场上最优惠的经纪费率
And we will offer you the best brokerage rates in the market
高摩就是以此闻名
Growmore is known for that
请坐
Please have a seat
谢谢你
Thank you
梅塔先生，我们也做过调查
Mr Mehta, weve done our research too
关于你 和你的经营理念
about you and your ways
[ Khemani ]我们在市场上也有朋友
[Khemani] We too have friends in the market
你有你自己的方法
You have your own methods
你喜欢挑战大玩家
And you love taking on the big players
- 事实上，先生-[ Khemani ]‘你有
- Actually, sir -[Khemani] And you have
有时用你自己的方式
faced huge losses at times
会面临巨大的损失
because of your own methods
但是，这也是真的
But, its also true that
你从来没有让你的客户遭受损失
youve never let your clients suffer a loss
甚至在上次市场崩溃之后也没有
Not even after the last market crash
你是一个正直的人
You are a man of integrity
谢谢你
Thank you
在这个圈子，经纪人与外国银行联手操纵报价
Here, brokers team up with foreign banks to manipulate quotes
为了他们和他们的客户的利益
for their and their clients benefit
我们今天见你不是为了安全起见
Were meeting you today, not because we want to play safe
而是因为我们想改变 SBI 的形象
But because we want to change the image of SBI
高摩是我们的首选
Growmore is at the top of our priority list
因为你知道如何去冒险
because you know how to take risks
这些外国银行及其经纪人多年来一直在抢劫我们
These foreign banks and their brokers have been looting us for years
该是我们整顿家务的时候了
Its high time we set our house in order
- 是不是?-当然
-[Khemani] Isnt it? - Absolutely
我们合作吧，梅塔先生
We are in business, Mr Mehta
[ Ajay ]很显然，他可能刚刚在金融字典里增加了一个新词
[Ajay] Apparently, he might just add a new word to the financial dictionary
银行家时代！
Bankerage!
这是什么? 新花招？
What is this? A new gimmick?
你不会喜欢这个的
Youre not going to like this one bit
哈沙德开始在货币市场建仓
Harshad has started taking positions in the money market too
还利用银行作掩护
and that too, by using banks as a front
赚取佣金
Theyre getting a commission
他称之为银行时代 ！
He calls it bankerage!
银行也乐于这么做，甚至还包括印度国家银行
And the banks are doing it happily Even SBI
不不不
No, no, no, AK
这很严重
This is serious
我总是说，经纪人持有任何头寸都是犯罪
Ive always said, its a crime for brokers to take any position
所有这一切使得哈萨德成为我们的竞争对手
And all this makes Harshad our competition now
我们必须密切注意他的一切行动
We must keep a close eye on all his actions
我是指，所有的行动
And I mean, all actions
我需要他所有交易的详细情况
I need the details of all his transactions
我们不能在这件事上马马虎虎
We cant be caught napping on this
绝对不能
No
我说，我为什么要为这样一件小事请你来呢?
[Pranav] I said, why would I take a favour from you for such a small matter?
我来找你要点大的东西
Id come to you for something big
- 我不要-嗯？
- Not for me - Huh?
一只脚踏进货币市场  你就放弃了糖果？
One foot in the money market and youve given up sweets?
不是放弃，而是控制
Not given up just controlling
你什么时候开始控制自己的？
When did you start controlling yourself?
这些日子，你不就是那个失控的人吗？
Well, these days, arent you the one whos out of control?
我已经看到你把 ACC 推得有多高 完全失控
Ive seen how high youve pushed ACC out of control
还在密切关注市场动向？
Keeping tabs on the market, huh?
看来猎豹错过了他的丛林！
Looks like the cheetah is missing his jungle!
但是现在的情况是，是时候抛弃 ACC 了
But the word is, its time to ditch ACC
马努和他的手下正在摩拳擦掌
Manu Bhai and his men are targeting it
如果他们开始做空，我就没有资金持有了
If they start shorting, I dont have the funds to hold on
这就是我们公牛的问题
This is the problem with us Bulls
当我们依赖市场获取资金的时候，那些看空者就会知道
The moment we depend on the market for funds, those bears get to know
顺便问一下，你需要多少钱？
By the way, how much do you need?
哈沙德说，现在是重返市场的最好时机
[Harshad] This is the right time to get back into the market
当然，谁阻止你了
[Ashwin] Sure Whos stopping you?
但是不要去追求 ACC
But dont go after ACC
听着，如果普拉纳夫没有资金，我们也没有什么宝藏箱
Look, if Pranav doesnt have the funds, its not like we have a treasure chest
卡纳拉银行想要购买一些证券，对吗？
Canara Bank wanted to buy some securities, right?
他们有寄支票来吗？
They were to send a cheque?
就是这个
There it is
哈沙德，我们应该从谁那里买债券呢？
Harshad, whom should we buy the bonds from?
Grindlays会有，对吧？
Grindlays will have, right?
一旦我们拿到收据，我会亲自把它们送到卡纳拉银行
Once we get the BRs, Ill deliver them personally to Canara Bank
我已经有一段时间没去那儿了
Its been a while since Ive been there
我们今天把这些支票全部存入我们的帐户
Lets deposit all these cheques into our account today
卡纳拉银行需要十天后的证券
Canara Bank needs the securities after ten days
哈沙德，你
Harshad, you
你疯了吗？
Are you out of your mind?
这不是我们的钱
This is not our money
如果我们想回到市场，这是我们的宝藏箱
If we want to get back in the market, this is our treasure chest
哈沙德，这是个远期交易
Harshad, its a ready forward deal
一旦 BR 到期，我们就得把钱退回去
Once the BR expires, well have to return the money
我们会的，还有整整十天的时间
And we will We have ten whole days
在那之前，这些钱无论如何都会在我们的账户里慢慢消失
Till then, this money will be rotting away in our account in any case
如果我们把它投资到市场上，钱就会增长，市场也会增长
If we invest it in the market, the money will grow and so will the market
事情败露的时候，我们的麻烦也会增加
And when it comes out in the open, our troubles will grow too
不会有任何麻烦，我们不偷东西
There wont be any trouble We are not stealing
钱在我们的账户里，我们怎么处理这笔钱不关别人的事
The money is lying in our account What we do with it is nobodys concern
想象一下，我们10天能赚多少钱！
Imagine How much profit we can make in 10 days!
[ Sucheta ]公牛回到了交易所
[Sucheta] The Bull was back in BSE
他的第一个赌注就是 ACC
And his first bet, was on ACC
而熊正在摧毁 ACC
The bears were destroying ACC
但是他们没有任何暗示
But they didnt have even the slightest hint
这一次，哈沙德不仅仅是有钱
that this time, Harshad didnt just have money
他拥有整个财富集市
he had the whole bazaar of wealth
通常为了节省安全交易的时间,
Often, to save time in security dealings,
银行会将资金直接存入经纪人的账户
banks would deposit funds directly into brokers accounts
这样经纪人就可以在买入之前敲定最好的交易
so that the broker could crack the best deals before buying
哈萨德看到了这里的漏洞
Harshad saw the loophole here
现在这笔钱存在他的账户里，他又开始投资股市了
With this money now lying in his account, he began investing in the share market again
这是一个缓慢的系统
It was a slow system
所以这笔钱通常会在经纪人的账户里存两个星期
so the money would often remain in the brokers account for upto a fortnight
哈萨德可以轻易地把它当作自己的
It was readily available for Harshad to use as his own
推高任何他喜欢的股票
and push up any stock he liked
通过在股票市场上轮换银行资金
By rotating banking funds in the share market
他赚了很多钱
he was making so much profit
他开始以较低的佣金进行货币市场交易
that he began making money market deals at lower commissions
银行得到了最好的交易
Banks were getting the best deals
哈尔沙德赚的钱也越来越多
And Harshad was making more and more profit
对他来说，货币市场已经变成了赚钱的市场
The money market had turned into a money-making market for him
当然，我们可以加入
Sure, we can join this
夫人，在孟买这样一个黄金地段，有这么大的一套公寓，是很少见的
Madam, a flat this big in Bombay at such a prime location, is rare
Sensex 指数触及1400点
The Sensex is touching 1400
我们应该在1600点时出手
At 1600 we should start selling
我希望你不介意
I hope you are okay with that
股票市场是你的领域
Share markets are your territory
做你认为最好的事情
Do what you feel is best
但是，如果指数进一步上升呢？
But, what if the index rises even more?
哈尔沙德非常乐观
Harshad is being really bullish
快点! 快点，他是谁? 他有多少钱？
Come on! Come on, who is he? How much money does he have?
他不能再买下去了
He cant just go on buying more and more
看吧，你没明白我的意思
See, you are not getting the point
他有钱
He has the funds
他正在利用银行资金推高市场
Hes using banking funds to push up the markets
他反应很快？
Hes caught on quick?
他在玩我们的一个小把戏
Hes using a trick out of our book
唯一的区别是，我们这样做是安全的，而且用一个优雅的方式
The only difference is that we do it safely, and in a classy way
而且他的方式是无阶级的，粗鲁的
And he does it in a classless, crude way
不
No
我们需要一个策略来阻止他
We need a strategy to stop him
用我们的银行资金做空市场
Lets use our banking funds to short the markets
我们必须尽我们所能
We have to do whatever we can
攻击，分散，交火
Attack, divide, engage
最终击败
and defeat
渣打希望获得价值2亿卢比的证券
Stanchart wants securities worth 200 crores
- 所以呢?-所以是什么意思？
- So? - What do you mean, so?
我们的银行没有一家持有如此巨额的证券
None of our banks hold such a huge amount of securities
告诉我
Tell me something
我们多久向银行提供一次实物证券？
How often have we delivered physical securities to banks?
我们有没有亲自交给他们？
Have we ever handed them over in person?
但是，兄弟，我们必须给 BRs 作为证据，不是吗？
But brother, we have to give BRs as proof, dont we?
一旦银行开出收据,
Once the bank gives the receipt,
这意味着他们正在确认收到的证券
It means theyre confirming that the securities received
像驴子一样思考，你将永远是一个驴子
Think like a donkey and youll remain one
什么？
What?
渣打银行想要价值2亿的 BRs，对吗？
Stanchart wants BRs worth 200 crores, right?
- 是的-所以我们会给 BRs
- Yes - So, well give BRs
这不正是花旗银行的集团所做的吗？
Isnt that what Citibank cartel does?
哈沙德，这种事我做不到?
Harshad Bhai, how can I do what you are asking me to?
- 这不合法-这没什么不对的
- This is not legal - Theres nothing wrong in it
但是，如果我没有证券，我怎么能够发行 BRs 给他们 ？
But if I dont have the securities, how can I issue BRs to them?
我怎样才能卖掉我没有的东西还给你一张收据呢？
How can I sell something I dont have and give you a receipt for it?
- 这是不对的-这不是不对，这是生存
- This is wrong - This is not wrong Its survival
我知道你连员工工资都开不出来
Im aware that you dont even have funds to pay salaries
因此，这是挽救你的一个可行的方法
So, this is a sure-shot way to rescue your bank from its losses
这很简单
Its very simple
渣打银行想要价值2亿的证券？
Stanchart wants securities worth 200 crores?
你只需要开出收据
You just issue the BRs
把收据给他们
Give them the receipt
一旦他们拿到收据，20亿卢比就会打到你的账户上
As soon as they get the receipt, 200 crores will be in your account
其中有四千万是你的
Of which, 4 crores will be yours Bankerage
15天内，我会还给他们20亿卢比
Within 15 days, Ill return 200 crores to them
他们会把 BRs 还给你，然后把它们撕掉，如果你愿意的话
Theyll return the BRs to you Then tear them off, if you like
他们将得到证券
They will get the securities
你会得到佣金
You will get a commission
花旗银行的所有业务都是通过 BRs 进行的
Citibank does all its business through BRs
听着，先生，即使你知道,
And look sir, even you know,
在任何交易中，实物证券都不会被交换
that physical securities are never exchanged in any deal
[ Sucheta ]到1990年底，印度正走向经济危机
[Sucheta] By the end of 1990, India was heading towards an economic crisis
印度央行行长知道
The RBI Governor knew
银行将在印度经济复苏中发挥关键作用
banks will play a pivotal role in Indias economic revival
但是印度储备银行也开始注意到
But the RBI had also begun to notice irregularities
在银行的安全交易中违规行为
in the security dealings of banks
但这是一个前数字时代
But this was a pre-digital era
通常需要好几天才能追踪到一笔交易
when it often took days to trace a transaction
找到一份文件需要几个月的时间
and months to locate a file
对印度储备银行来说，这将是一场乏味且持久的战斗
For RBI, this was going to be a tedious battle
印度联合银行，巴罗达银行
United Bank of India, Bank of Baroda
印度银行、卡纳拉银行和印度银行
Bank of India, Canara Bank and Indian Bank
与银行业务运营和发展部联系
Talk to the Department of Banking Operations and Development
我要所有这些银行的安全部门
I want the security departments of all these banks
彻底检查
thoroughly checked and inspected
先生 呃
Sir Uh
- 什么事，高希?-先生，花旗银行？
- Yes, Ghosh? - Sir, Citibank?
嗯，这是一家外国银行，我们必须小心
Hmmm Its a foreign bank We have to be careful
我们的经济仍在复苏，尚未企稳
Our economy is still recovering It hasnt stabilised yet
我们仍然依赖他们安排的贷款
We are still dependent on the loans arranged by them
这样
Do one thing
给他们一个非正式的警告
Give them an informal warning
还有，高希
And, Ghosh
让它看起来像一个定期的审计
Make it look like a regular audit
不是调查
Not an investigation
这件事不应该传出去
The matter shouldnt leave this room
不能让媒体知道，谢谢
The Press mustnt get to know of it Thank you
第五家银行是哪家? 印度银行？
And which is the fifth bank? Indian Bank?
太好了，你确定吗？
Great Are you sure?
你确定今天所有这些银行都会接受检查吗？
And youre sure there will be inspections in all these banks today?
女士，这只是前五家银行
[Man] Madam, these are only the first five banks
印度储备银行将会盯上其他银行
The RBI will go after other banks too
所有这些混蛋现在都暴露了
All these b******s stand exposed now
即使是像卡拉季银行这样的小银行
Even small banks like Bank of Karaj
那里根本没有证券账户
No account of securities there either
RBI（印度储备银行）的计划是什么? 我是说，他们的下一步计划是什么？
So, whats RBI planning? I mean, whats their next step going to be?
像往常一样，他们会发布有关证券买卖的通知
[Man] As usual, theyll issue a circular on the buying and selling of securities
印度储备银行将发布新规则
RBI will issue new rules
还会增加一些分数，还有什么
And theyll add some more points, what else?
你能把我和任何经纪人联系起来吗？
Can you link me to any broker?
哦，不行，除非这次检查的消息公之于众
[Man] Oh no Unless the news of this inspection goes public
所有的经纪人都会守口如瓶
all the brokers will keep their mouth shut
有没有人有理由会开口？
Does anybody ever speak without a reason?
但是理由是可以创造的，不是吗？
But reasons can be created, right?
[ Sucheta ]尽管哈尔沙德和印度储备银行都把目光放在了银行身上
[Sucheta] While both Harshad and the RBI kept their sights focused on the banks
我仍在专注于我在《印度时报》的新工作
I was focused on my new job with The Times of India
我们谁也不知道我们的道路很快就会相交
None of us knew that our paths were going to cross very soon
也没有一家银行的名称或来源
Nor is there the name of a bank nor a source
苏切塔，没有任何名字，我不能发表这个
Sucheta, without any names, I cant print this
我的线人在其中一家银行工作
My source works in one of these banks
这个故事百分之百是真的
The story is 100 percent legit
也许吧，但是有人能证明吗？
Maybe But can anyone confirm it?
- 我不能-拉杰迪普，这个故事很重要
- I cant - Rajdeep, this story is huge
而且会越来越重要，但只有当你发表这个
And it will only get bigger, but only if you print this
- 苏切塔，你知道我的答案-你要相信我
-[Rajdeep] Sucheta, you know my answer - You need to trust me
当其他媒体都在赞扬拉詹 · 皮莱的时候
When the rest of the media was singing Rajan Pillais praises
是我举报他在新加坡触犯了法律，结果越来越严重
I was the one who reported his brush with the law in Singapore and it snowballed
我有同样的预感，把它发表出来
I have the same hunch with this Print it
只有这样，银行体系中的每个人才会知道
Only then will everyone in the banking system know
内部消息不可能永远隐藏
that inside information cant stay hidden forever
如果我们发表了这个之后就没人开口了
And if we print this, and no one opens their mouth after that
然后呢? 我不能冒险把这个放在头版
Then? I cant risk putting this on the front page
- 你会把它放在哪里?-财经板块
- Where will you put it? - The financial section
绝对不是，先生
No chance, sir No chance
我可以肯定，这个消息绝对不是从我们这边泄露出去的
Im absolutely sure, this information hasnt leaked from our end
是某家银行寄来的
Its from some bank
但是既然这个消息已经公开了
But since this news is already out in the open
我们可以宣布一次常规审计来确认违规行为吗？
can we announce a proper audit to confirm the irregularities?
公众不想接受审计
The public doesnt want an audit
不，高希，那没用的
No, Ghosh, that wont work
发布一个指示并与媒体分享
Issue a directive and share it with the press
每个人都必须清楚地知道
Everyone must know clearly
印度储备银行已经发布了关于 BRs 使用的严格指导方针
that the RBI has issued strict guidelines on the use of BRs
凯迪亚告诉我，你拒绝了所有的远期交易
[Tyagi] Kedia told me that youve refused all ready forward deals?
先生，印度储备银行就在我们后面
Sir, The RBI is on our tail, sir
但是如果你都掩盖好了，又怎么会有问题呢？
But where is the problem if youre all covered up?
先生，印度储备银行已经发布了一份新的通知
Sir, RBI has issued a new circular
先生，你没有看过指导方针吗？
Havent you read the guidelines, Sir?
看看这个，先生，这是严格的命令
Look at this, sir These are strict orders
所有准备就绪的远期交易
All ready forward transactions
不管是通过 SGL 还是 BR
whether through the mechanism of SGL or BR
应该在同一天反映在其投资帐户
should be reflected on the same day in its investment account
一家银行与另一家银行之间的交易
Transactions between one bank and another bank
不应该通过经纪人的账户
should not be put through the brokers accounts
银行不应充当任何经纪客户的代理人
Banks should not act as agents for any broker clients
最重要的是
And the most important part
所有交易都应严格按照市场利率进行
All transactions should be at market rates, strictly
还有
And
- 你从来不按市价交易-别说了
- You never deal at market rates - Stop it
是RBI，又不是 CBI（印度中央调查局）
Its RBI, not the CBI
这些只是指导方针，不是法律
And these are guidelines, not the law
这是印度
And this is India
[ Tyagi ]你知道这里什么都没发生过
[Tyagi] You know nothing ever happens here
如果你还想继续做生意
And look, if you want to stay in business
那你就得做生意了，对吧？
then youll have to do business, right?
对不起，特亚吉先生
Im sorry, Mr Tyagi
但我们会坚持指导方针
But well stick to the guidelines for any business
你是说我老了吗？
You tell me Am I old?
新一代人就是不听
This new generation just wont listen
他们把有经验的人叫做老人，把我们推开
They call the experienced, old and push us away
我告诉我儿子
I told my son
货币市场是一团糟，别掺和进来
that the money market is a mess Dont get into it
但是他没有听进去，你看看，现在每一笔交易都是一场斗争
But he didnt listen And look Today, every deal is a struggle
苏雷什，一个人的年龄取决于他的思想
Suresh, a person is only as old as his thoughts
年龄只是一个数字
Age is just a number
- [苏雷什]‘你为什么不给我儿子解释一下? -但是你从来没有介绍过我们！
-[Suresh] Why dont you explain this to my son? - But you never introduced us!
我会解释所有关于年龄的问题，也要跟进那个虚假BR的报道
I wouldve explained all about age and also taken a follow-up on that fake BR story
哦，那么，我现在没用了？
Oh So, Im useless now?
新的消息来源，新的故事？
New source New story?
苏雷什 好吧，为什么我叫你苏雷什？
Suresh Okay, why do I call you Suresh?
因为你是我的朋友，而不仅仅是我的消息来源
Because youre a friend and not just a source
每个人都压制了 BR 的报道
Everyone has suppressed the BR story
如果我没有后续报道，这件事就不了了之了
And if I dont get a follow-up, it will die
好的，我见到他的时候会和他谈谈的
Okay, Ill talk to him when I see him
- 他可能会同意-他不是在办公室吗？
- He might agree - Isnt he in the office?
他每时每刻都在办公室里
Hes in office 24/7
但是尽管他是我的邻居  他甚至都不和我说话，更不用说见面了
But despite being next-door he doesnt even talk to me, let alone meeting
好吧，我先走了
Okay Ill take your leave
[ Sucheta ]对不起
[Sucheta] Sorry
- 我只需要两分钟-你 你在这儿干什么？
- I just need two minutes - What What are you doing here?
我是印度时报的苏切塔 · 达拉尔
I am Sucheta Dalal from Times of India
[ DT ]我知道你是谁
[DT] I know who you are
我不想和你说话
I dont want to speak to you
听着，没关系，你父亲已经认识我了
Listen, its okay Your father already knows me
- 我只需要一点点信息-要我叫保安吗？
- I just need a little bit of info - Do you want me to call the security?
不不 请不要误会我
No no Please, dont misunderstand me
- 我只需要一点点信息-[铃声响起]
- I just need a little bit of info -[bell rings]
请离开
Please leave
好吧，如果你想聊聊，你爸爸有我的电话号码
Okay, your father has my number if you ever want to talk
好的，抱歉，谢谢
Okay Sorry Thank you
印度储备银行正在检查账簿的每一页每一行
The RBI is checking every line from every page of every book
好吧，让我们像银行家一样谈谈
Okay Lets talk like bankers
忘了证券吧
Forget the securities
我肯定你能借给我一笔钱？
Im sure you can give me a loan?
告诉我，你们能提供多少信用额度？
Tell me What line of credit can you offer?
贷款需要资金，不是吗？
To give a loan, I need funds, dont I?
我没有拒绝，但是我们面临资金短缺
Im not refusing But were facing a major crunch for funds
你也是因为资金问题被困在这里的，对吧？
You too are stranded because of funds, huh?
好吧，那如果
Okay What if I bring customers
我带来一个能在这家银行存一大笔钱的客户？
who will deposit large amounts in this bank?
那么你会给我贷款，对吗？
Then you will give me a loan, right?
印度储备银行已经用它的指导方针束缚了整个系统
[Sucheta] RBI had chained the whole system with its guidelines
哈沙德知道，即使是熊市集团也是在没有现金的情况下进行演习
Harshad knew that even the bear cartel was on a dry-run with no cash
现在是时候走在他们前面了
This was the time to get ahead of them
停泊费，燃料费 一共
Docking charges, fuel charges altogether
他们每周收集20到25亿卢比
they make a weekly collection of 20 to 25 crores
还有那个，液体
And that too, liquid
在码头和海里，一切都是液态的
Everything is liquid at the docks and in the sea
想象一下
Just imagine
如果我们把他们所有的资金都转移到RICO银行呢？
What if we channelize all their funds to RICO?
然后资金最终会回到我们手中
Then the funds will eventually come back to us
等等，兄弟，告诉我，你是国王吗？
Wait a minute, brother Tell me something Are you a king?
或者一个 lootsesea？
Or a LOOTSESEA?
- lootsesea?-七海之王？
- LOOTSESEA? - Lord Of The Seven Seas?
你一招手，码头会把他们所有的资金都投入 RICO？
That you will beckon, and the docks will pour their entire fund into RICO?
胡说！
Rubbish!
每个人都会向利益低头
Everyone bows down to profit
我知道如何编造一个关于利润的故事
And I know how to weave a story about profit
还有布尚，这些资金应该投资到哪里
And Bhushan, where these funds should be invested
是主席的特权
is the prerogative of the chairman
我们要做的就是说服主席
All we have to do, is convince the chairman
你打算编什么故事? 请解释一下
And what is this story you plan to weave? Please explain
瞧，RICO 没有资金贷款
Look, RICO has no funds to give a loan
如果这些钱到了那里，他们就会得到资金
If this money goes there, theyll get funds
我们可以贷款
and well get a loan
贷款的利率是多少? 11% ？
Whats the interest rate for a loan? 11 percent?
假设我们以12% 的利率贷款
Assume, we take this loan at 12 percent
[ Bhushan ]也就是说，1% 给主席
[Bhushan] That means, one percent for the chairman
但是兄弟，钱还是会从我们的口袋里拿出来的，对吧
But brother, the money will still go from our pocket, right?
那么，就这样吧
[Harshad] So, let it
当我们将这笔贷款投资于市场并获得巨额利润时
When we invest this loan in the market and make a huge profit
这1% 或2%根本不值得一提
this one or two percent will fade in comparison
听着，盖松德先生，你必须把钱存在某一家银行
Look, Mr Gaithonde, you have to deposit your money in one bank or the other
那为什么不把钱存到 RICO 银行呢？
Why dont you deposit it in RICO bank this time?
你将从银行获得利息
You will earn an interest from the bank
而且我对你的利益也很感兴趣
but Im interested in your interest too
你明白的，不是吗？
You understand, dont you?
给我点时间，让我考虑一下
Give me some time Let me think about it
来，听我解释
Come, let me explain
听着，我是股票市场的人
Look, Im a man of the share market
因此，与其说我相信时间，不如说我相信即时交易
So, rather than in time, I believe in instant deals
如果我们给它太多的时间，价值可能下降
If we give it too much time, the value might drop
这笔交易的价值可能也会下降
And the value of this deal might drop too
你确定阿米塔布·巴沙坎的西装是在这里制造的吗？
Are you sure Amitabh Bachchan gets his suits made here?
是的，我的也是
Yes Mine too
很好
Thats good
哈尔沙德不亚于证交所的巴彻
Harshad is no less than the Bachchan of BSE
我们愤怒的年轻人独自对付花旗集团
Our angry young man, whos taken on the cartel all alone
- 对吧?-是啊
- Right? - Yeah
还有 Jobber 先生，生活不只是电影
And, Mr Jobber, life isnt a movie
还有爆米花和零食的休息时间
with an interval for popcorns and snacks
生活不断变化，没有什么是永恒的
Life keeps changing Nothings permanent
你怎么说，哈沙德？
What do you say, Harshad?
它可以是永久性的
It can be permanent
如果资金继续流动，我们将成为永久的牛市
If funds keep flowing, we will be permanent bulls
不只是牛市
Not just Bull
大牛市
Big Bull
所有银行都在印度储备银行的监控范围内
Hey, all banks are in RBIs radar
他们甚至在放屁之前都要咨询印度储备银行
They have to consult the RBI even before they fart
处理安全业务的旧方式已经过时了
Gone are the old ways of conducting security business
你知道《印度时报》的苏切塔 · 达拉尔吗? 她正在写一篇文章
You know Sucheta Dalal, from Times of India? Shes writing an article
如果你的名字和 BRs 有关
If your name crops up in relation to BRs
她会敲你的门，小心点
shell be knocking at your door Be careful
她找我又能怎样？
And what will she do once she reaches me? Huh?
我不再做证券交易了
I dont deal in securities anymore
你不做证券交易是什么意思？
What do you mean you dont deal in securities?
我的意思是，我有一吨的政府资金
What I mean Pranav Bhai is that there is a ton of government money
在警察局吃灰
gathering dust in PSUs
所以，让我们把钱投进证交所
So, lets invest that money in BSE
政府也要赚点钱，对吧？
Government must earn some profit too, right?
主席先生，坦率地说，政府保安部需要一个新的方法
Sir, frankly speaking, government PSUs need a fresh approach
你很清楚，印度石油天然气公司有很多钱，但是没有计划
You know well, ONGC has so much money, but no plan
事实上，当我们和部长讨论我们的想法时，他明确地说
In fact, when we discussed our ideas with the minister, he clearly said
去见见那瓦拉卡先生，他是个有远见的人
Go meet Mr Nawalakha He is the man with a vision
但是梅塔先生
But, Mr Mehta
这是政府的钱
This is the governments money
我们不能允许它投资股票市场
We cant allow it to be invested in the stock market
但我不是这个意思
But thats not what Im saying
我想说的是，投资银行的 PMS 计划
All Im saying is, invest in the PMS schemes of banks
听着，先生，我的工作是赚钱
Look, sir My job is to make profit
我也会为政府创造利润
And I will make profit for the government too
我们只需要符合我们的愿景
We just need to match our vision
[苏切塔]现在，哈尔沙德有了这样一个资金来源
[Sucheta] Now, Harshad had Such a source of money
没有人能想象得到
which nobody could have imagined
不仅仅是印度石油天然气公司
Not just ONGC
像印度煤炭这样的大型政府机构
but huge public sectors units like Coal India
NHPC，NTPC，和 IRFC 的钱
NHPC, NTPC, and IRFC money
也开始直接投资于银行保险公司
started getting invested in the bank PMSs directly
间接地，在股票市场上
and indirectly, in the share market
这个世界只是一个停顿 每个人都是一个旅行者
This world is but a halt and everyone a traveller
那么为什么愚蠢的人，把自己困在财富和名望的陷阱里
why then does the foolish man trap himself in the trappings of wealth and fame
不要相信这一刻  很快它就会消失，在你知道去哪里之前
dont trust this moment soon it will be gone, before you know where
毕竟，生活不过是两天的集市
After all, life is but a two-day fair
但是有些人问了很多问题
But some people ask a lot of questions
公司是做什么的? 它生产什么?
What does the company do? What does it produce?
没有人愿意长期投资
Nobody wants to invest for the long term
收取你的利润，然后抽身出来
Book your profits and pull out
那就告诉他们
Then tell them
马自达是哈尔沙德投资的公司
Mazda is Harshad Mehtas company
只要这一句就够了
Thats all it takes
这是内部消息
This is insider news
哈尔沙德投资了马自达工业
Harshad Bhai has invested in Mazda Industries
现在看看它是如何变化的
Now see how it zooms
哈尔沙德很快就成了市场上的传奇
[Sucheta] Harshad was fast becoming a market legend
他只要发出一个信号，市场就会出现逆转
One signal from him, and the tide would turn in the market
根据哈尔沙德的说法，马自达这样闻所未闻的公司
On Harshads word, unheard-of companies like Mazda
也引起了人们的注意
also caught peoples attention
但对印度经济而言，1991年是一个奇怪的时期
[Sucheta] But 1991 was a strange time for the Indian economy
在经济危机中
In the middle of an economic crisis
钱德拉谢卡尔政府解散了
The Chandrashekhar government was dissolved
下一次选举是在曼达尔委员会抗议期间举行的
The next election took place in the midst of Mandal Commission protests
很难猜测选举结果
It was tough to guess the election result
但在第一轮投票之后
But after the first round of voting
前总理拉吉夫 · 甘地被暗杀
ex-Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi was assassinated
当选举结果公布的时候
And when the election results were announced
少数派政府在纳拉辛哈·拉奥的领导下成立
a minority government was formed under P V Narasimha Rao
但这些都没有影响到股市
But none of this impacted the share market
哈尔沙德把指数拉到了极高的水平
Harshad took the BSE index to astronomical heights
现在，没有人能阻止他的奔牛节了
Now, there was no one to stop his Bull Run
我的朋友，你什么也带不走
You will take nothing with you, my friend
你空手而来，走的时候也是空手，我的朋友
You came empty-handed And thats how you will go, my friend
在哈尔沙德之前，没有人能在市场上赚到这么多钱
Before Harshad, no one had made such wealth in the market
他的生活方式不亚于名人或电影明星
His lifestyle was no less than a celebrity or a film star
他白手起家的故事
With his rags to riches story
他已经成为每个普通印度人的英雄
he had become a hero for every common Indian
每个人都想成为哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
And everybody wanted to be Harshad Mehta
这是不是有点过了？
Isnt this a bit much?
这个哈尔沙德 · 梅塔现在越界了
This Harshad Mehta is crossing the line now
他已经超越了自己的极限
The m**********r is crossing his limits
肉体和灵魂只有一个真理
Of this body and this soul theres only one truth
你必须注意你的行动，收获命运的甜蜜果实
You must watch your actions to reap destinys sweet fruit
所以说伟大的圣人这个世界是虚假的事情
So say the great saints this world is a false affair
毕竟，生活不过是两天的集市
After all, life is but a two-day fair
你给这个世界带来了什么? 你又能从这个世界上带走什么?
What did you bring into this world And what can you take away from this world
毕竟，生活不过是两天的集市
After all, life is but a two-day fair
股票市场的逻辑很简单
The logic of the stock market is very easy
闭上你的眼睛，随便选一支股票，然后投资它
Close your eyes, pick any stock and invest in it
获胜或失败的机会总是一半一半
The chances of winning or losing are always 50-50
别笑，这是事实
Dont laugh, its a fact
你知道吗，1964年在美国，人们让一只猴子选择15支股票
Did you know, in 1964 in the US, a monkey was made to select 15 scrips
也是这样，蒙着眼睛扔飞镖
That too, by throwing darts with a blindfold
与此同时，一位金融专家又选择了另外15支股
And at the same time, a financial expert selected another 15 scrips
结果是什么？
What was the result?
猴子赢了
The 15 scrips selected by the monkey, won
他们赚了一大笔钱
They made a huge profit
市场有一个简单的哲学: 投资，放松
The market has a simple philosophy Invest, and relax
- 他也是这么做的-不
- Even he did the same - No
我的意思是，是的，有一点
I mean yes, a little bit
叔叔，能给我签个名吗？
Uncle, can I get your autograph, please?
亲爱的，他们叫我阿米塔布·巴沙坎，但实际上我不是他
Dear, they call me Amitabh Bachchan, but Im actually not him
我告诉过你，我不想要这些旧的
I had told you, I dont want these old ones
让我看看新的东西
Show me something new
这是国王的座驾
This is the car of the King of Partan, Harshad Bhai
整个印度只有一辆
A single piece in all of India
1200 CC的发动机
And it has a 1200 CC engine
亲爱的，现在是我的时代
Darling, this is my time
所以不只是你们国王的车，我还可以买下他的宫殿
So not just your Kings car, I can buy his palace
- 给我看点新的，进口的-你知道进口车是怎么回事
- Show me something new Imported -[Dealer] You know how it is with imported cars
我们一个月几乎都没有一辆
We hardly get one in a month
下个月有一辆雷克萨斯从迪拜开过来
Theres a Lexus coming from Dubai next month
但是，阿贾伊·凯迪亚
But, Ajay Kedia
你可能认识他
You might know him
他的公司已经预定了
His company has already booked it
多少钱？
How much is it?
- 我给你看点别的 -多少钱？
- Harshad Bhai, Ill show you something else - How much is it?
四百五十万卢比
Its 45 lakhs
你收预付款了吗？
Have you taken an advance?
不，我没收，但我已经答应他了，我保证
No, Ive not taken any But Ive given him My word
那么汽车应该从迪拜直接送到我家
Then the car should be delivered from Dubai directly to my house
我给你五百五十万卢比
Ill give you 55 lakhs
四百五十万买车，一百万买你说的话
Forty-five for the car and ten for your word
你喜欢这辆车吗？
Do you like the car?
很好，但是你要这么多车干什么？
Its nice But what will you do with so many cars?
我们已经有15到20辆车了
We already have 15 to 20 cars
你不喜欢吗？
Didnt you like it?
不，这很好但是一辆车有什么用呢？
No, its good But what good will a car do?
很多用处
A lot
金钱吸引金钱
Money attracts money
人们必须知道
People must know
米哈特人不亚于安巴尼人或塔塔人
that the Mehtas are no less than Ambanis or Tatas
- 明白了吗?-大哥，我们不应该这么张扬
- Got it? - Bhai, we dont want to become so big
会带来厄运
It can bring bad luck
忘掉这些迷信，坐在车里享受吧
Forget these superstitions Sit in the car and enjoy
我会的
I will
但我想你已经忘记了
But I think youve forgotten
当你还小的时候，一个牧师看了你的星座运势
When you were small, Shantilal Mehta had shown your horoscope to a priest
他说你在钱的问题上运气不好
he said that you are going to be unlucky in matters of money
当你口袋里有钱的时候，运气不好也不会怎么样
When theres money in your pocket, Bad luck makes no difference
这是我的占星术
This is my astrology
来吧
Come on now
嘿，聪明鬼！
Hey, smarty!
来吧！
Come on now!
- 坐后面来吧-来
- Sit at the back, come on - Come
[电话铃声]
[phone ringing]
你好
Hello
是的，是谁？
Yes, whos it?
好的，请稍等
Yes, hold on a minute
电话
Phone
- 是谁?-他说是从德里来的
- Whos it? - Says hes from Delhi
- 你好?-你好，梅塔先生
- Hello? -[Swami] Greetings, Mehta ji
我是圣斯瓦米，来自德里
Its Santswami, from Delhi
晚上好，阁下
Hari Om, Swami ji
很抱歉在这个时候打扰你
Sorry to trouble you at this hour
时间不是烦恼
The time is not the worry
烦恼的是，你已经打过电话了
[Harshad] The worry is that youve called
只要我在这里，你就没有理由担心
While Im here, you have no reason to worry
[ Swami ]你在选举期间给政党提供的所有帮助
[Swami] All the help youve extended to the parties during elections
受到这里每个人的赞赏
[Swami]is appreciated by everyone here
这个国家和政府在选举之后可能经历了一些变化
The country and the government may have undergone some changes after the elections
但是在德里，每个人都想和你保持同样的关系
But in Delhi, everyone would like to maintain the same relations with you
阁下，我希望有机会为政府服务
Swami ji, I would love an opportunity to serve the government
[ Swami ]你很快就会有机会的，我们很快就会见面的
[Swami] You will soon get the opportunity, and we shall meet soon